We're going to go over the MIPS R10K and implementation of the MIPS 4 ISA.
In the last lecture, we introduced the scoreboard implementation for out-of-order execution as
well as an intro on register renaming and speculation.
Now we'll be describing the MIPS R10K implementation, which handles false dependencies as well
as speculation and precise state.
So with the scoreboard, false dependencies became hazards and we were unable to provide
support for misspeculations.
The underlying reason for this is the right backstage is actually a combination of two
fundamental operations.
One, we need to propagate a result to younger dependent instructions.
This is okay to be done out of order.
And two, we need to write a result into the actual register file.
This would be better to be done in order so that at any point in time, we have a proper
snapshot of the state of all registers as if no one had executed out of order.
So what the MIPS R10K processor does is replaces the scoreboard with the reorder buffer or
ROB.
Its goal is to buffer completed results en route to the register file so that no matter
what arbitrary order the instructions finish executing, we can push their results to the
register file in order.
With this, we break up the right backstage into two new stages.
Complete is an out-of-order stage where after executing the operation, the instruction then
writes its result to the ROB in order to pass the value to any dependents.
Then retire is actually an in-order stage that comes after completion.
And its goal is to allow instructions to commit their changes into the register file and leave
the pipeline in the order that they were fetched.
Note that retire is sometimes also called commit or graduate.
This is a conceptual idea.
We'll get into the details of how to implement this.
The MIPS R10K employs register renaming, which as discussed removes WAR and WAW hazards by
effectively having multiple physical versions of architectural registers.
This completely eliminates the architectural register file.
Instead, we use a physical register file, and the map table simply tracks which physical
register currently holds the most recent value of each architectural register.
The free list keeps track of all unallocated physical registers.
To avoid running out of physical registers, the physical register file should be as large
as the number of architectural registers in the ISA plus the number of ROB entries.
This ensures enough physical registers for the worst case scenario where every single
instruction in the ROB is modifying a register.
An important question is, when is it safe to put physical registers back into the free
list?
When an instruction retires, the currently mapped physical register can't be freed
because younger instructions may still need to read this value.
However, the previously mapped physical register can now be freed upon retirement.
Why is this?
Because all instructions that will ever read this previous value must have already been
retired by now, if it's our turn to retire and we're overriding this register.
Now we'll describe the operation of our MIPS R10K processor.
Note that this is simply one manifestation of the principles of the original MIPS R10K
work.
Different implementations and variations are certainly possible.
We'll discuss a simplified MIPS R10K-like processor for the purposes of this course.
We'll make the following assumptions.
We'll assume that the front end stages, that is fetch, decode, and dispatch, are scalar.
Modern systems are likely to be able to fetch and decode multiple instructions in parallel.
We'll also assume that branches are resolved at the execute stage, and each reservation
station, which is a buffer for instructions waiting to perform an operation, each one
is bound to a functional unit.
That is, if our pipeline has three load units, then we'll have three reservation stations,
each dedicated to one load unit.
Let's describe the necessary hardware structures for the R10K processor.
First, we introduce reservation stations.
As just discussed, this is a buffer for tracking which instructions are waiting to use a specific
functional unit and tracking which operand registers they're waiting for.
Then we also have the ROB, map table, and free list, as previously discussed.
Now we'll illustrate how each pipeline stage is performed using the example add instruction
shown.
The fetch and decode stages are effectively still the same.
We need to get the instruction from memory, update the PC, and decode the operation and
operands.
As with the scoreboard, the dispatch stage is in order and initializes important hardware
structures.
First, we need to check for structural hazards.
If either there's no available reservation station, the reorder buffer is full, or there's
no free physical register on the free list, then we need to stall.
Once these structures are made available, we need to allocate a reservation station,
consult the map table to get the physical registers of our operands, as well as the
ready bits and record them in the reservation station.
In if our instruction writes to a register, we allocate a new physical register from the
free list and update the map table, clearing the ready bit.
Finally, we allocate the next entry in the reorder buffer, recording the old and new
physical register mappings.
Like in scoreboard, the issue stage is where instructions wait for their true dependences
to be resolved.
The only difference is now the wait in a reservation station as opposed to in the scoreboard.
An instruction must also wait here if there are no available functional units.
This is only possible in implementations where the number of reservation stations exceeds
the number of functional units.
So in these cases, an instruction will have to wait until a functional unit frees up.
In our simple implementation, we just assume a 1 to 1 ratio of reservation stations to
functional units.
Once an instruction is ready to issue, it moves into the functional unit and frees up
its reservation station.
The execute stage is identical to before, though note that different operations may
take more cycles to execute than others.
Complete is one of the new stages in R10K.
Its goal is to resolve RAW dependences.
If an instruction produces an output, the result will be written to the allocated physical
register.
Then the map table and all reservation stations that are currently waiting for this register
will be notified that it's ready to be read.
So in this example, the add instruction writes its result into physical register P1, which
sets the ready bit in the map table as well as the ready bits of the dependent instructions
in the reservation stations.
In this figure, the ready bits are shown as plus signs.
The last stage is retire.
This is the only in-order stage in the back end, and since it's in order, only the oldest
unretired instruction is allowed to retire at any cycle.
So even if an instruction has completed every other stage, it cannot perform the retire
operations until it's at the head of the reorder buffer.
Once an instruction is finally at the head of the reorder buffer and has entered the
retire stage, it does two key things.
First, it frees the old physical register that was mapped to its destination architectural
register.
In this example, this is P5, which was recorded in the ROB entry.
As discussed previously, it is now safe to free P5 here because any instructions that
needed to read P5 must have now retired since our add instruction is next in line to retire.
The second thing we need to do is free up the ROB entry, which makes the next instruction
the head.
Two additional things happen in retire.
If we're a store instruction, now is actually when we perform the write to memory instead
of in the execute stage.
The reason for this is to maintain precise state in the event of misspeculation or exceptions.
If we had performed the store operation during the execute stage, we risk modifying memory
and then later realizing that we need to flush the store.
Once a store instruction is ready to retire and is at the head of the ROB, only then can
we guarantee that it won't get flushed anymore so we can finally write to memory.
Any exceptions are also handled here so that we make sure the exceptions are always handled
in order.
Now let's see the MIPS R10K processor in action within an example program.
The top shows the pipeline diagram and the vertical line shows which point in time we're
currently in.
We'll go over how each of the hardware structures are updated at each cycle.
So at the end of cycle 2, the load instruction has been decoded and the branch instruction
has been fetched.
These stages don't affect the structures we're showing here.
Moving on to the end of cycle 3, the load has been dispatched.
As shown, we allocate a reservation station for the load and record the physical register
of its operand.
The load only has one input operand, which is register S0, and according to the map table,
this is currently mapped to physical register P6, which is ready.
Since the load is writing to register T0, it needs to allocate a new physical register
from the free list.
So we pop P1 from the free list and record it in the map table as well as the ROB entry.
And since T0 was previously mapped to P5, we record P5 in the ROB entry as well.
In the meantime, the branch is predicted to not be taken.
At the end of cycle 4, the load has issued since all its operands are ready.
Thus we remove it from the reservation station.
At the same time, the branch instruction is dispatched.
Its two operands are found to be mapped P1 and P4, but P1 is currently not ready since
it's being produced by the load instruction, hence the minus sign.
The branch is allocated in the ROB, and this time no register renaming needs to take place
because the branch instruction doesn't modify any registers.
Now in the end of cycle 5, the load instruction has started executing.
Here, we're assuming loads take three cycles to execute.
The branch is currently in the issue stage, but since not all of its operands are ready,
it needs to stay in the issue stage for the next cycle.
In the meantime, the add-i instruction is able to dispatch following the same procedure
as the others.
In cycle 6, not much changes.
The load is still executing, thus the branch and add-i instructions that are dependent
on it must continue to wait in issue.
At the same time, the subtract instruction is able to dispatch.
Similarly, in cycle 7, the add-i and branch continue to wait for the load to finish executing.
The subtract instruction, however, is able to successfully issue since both of its operands
are ready.
So then it frees up its reservation station.
Now the second add-i instruction is ready to dispatch, but it must actually stall because
of a structural hazard.
There are no free reservation stations for add-i available right now.
Now at the end of cycle 8, lots of things happen.
Finally, the load instruction is completed, so it was written its value to the physical
register file and notified all of its dependents that the data is ready.
So the dependents, which are now the branch and add-i instructions, are now able to successfully
issue in this stage, thus removing themselves from their reservation stations.
And because the first add-i instruction is able to exit its reservation station this
cycle, the second add-i instruction, which was stalled last cycle, can now successfully
dispatch as shown here.
In cycle 9, the load instruction is able to retire, so it removes itself from the ROB
and pushes the original physical register P5 into the free list.
Meanwhile, the subtract instruction completes, which passes its result to the second add-i
instruction, which is now able to issue.
And since the second add-i instruction issues and exits the reservation station, the third
add-i instruction can now be dispatched at the same time.
Now in cycle 10, both the branch and first add-i instructions complete.
The branch does nothing in the complete stage, while the add-i writes its result into the
physical register file and sets its ready bit in the map table as shown.
The subtract, which executed earlier, is now ready to retire, but it can't, since it's
not at the head of the ROB.
And meanwhile, the third add-i instruction successfully issues and leaves the reservation
station.
In cycle 11, three instructions are ready to retire, but only one instruction can be retired
in the cycle, and it has to be in order.
So only the branch instruction is able to retire, removing itself from the ROB.
Note that the second add-i instruction completes in this cycle, but it doesn't modify the
ready bit for register T0 in the map table.
That's because it no longer holds the most up-to-date value of register T0.
It can tell because its result went to physical register 8, but the map table entry is now
pointing to something else, P7, which implies that another instruction after is modifying
register T0, and that instruction is not ready, so the bit should remain cleared.
Now at the end of cycle 12, the first add-i instruction is able to retire and push P9 back
into the free list.
Meanwhile, the last add-i instruction is completed, and since it is the most recent version of
register T0, it sets the ready bit in the map table.
This process continues until the end of the program, and the final pipeline diagram is
shown above.
One of the big components of the MIPS R10K processor is its support for speculation and
precise state.
So how do we properly flush the pipeline in the event of mis-speculation or exception?
Like scoreboard, physical registers are written out of order in the complete stage.
The main difference is that unlike in scoreboard, the ROB and map table preserve the original
mappings of physical registers, just in case we end up needing to flush this instruction
later.
As long as we always retire instructions in order, we will always be able to revert any
changes we've made to registers or to memory in the event of mis-speculation.
To do this, we simply need to walk backwards through the ROB and roll back the contents
of the map table and the free list one by one.
Note that there's no need to modify the physical register file.
The data can stay there.
We only need to put physical registers back on the free list.
Let's walk through the process of handling mis-speculation using the example program
from earlier.
So earlier, we predicted the branch to be not taken, but what if after resolving it in
the execute stage, we find that it's actually taken?
How do we flush all of these instructions?
It's actually quite straightforward.
We just start from the youngest instruction and work backwards.
So in this case, the third add-i instruction is the youngest.
So we've removed it from the reservation station and the ROB.
Then we put its physical register P7 back into the free list and revert P8 back into
the map table.
Then we move on to the next youngest instruction and do the same thing.
We clear it from the ROB and revert the map table and the free list.
This process simply continues until we've cleared all ROB entries that came after the
branch instruction.
Then at this point, the branch is able to complete and we immediately start fetching
from the taken target PC.
So let's reiterate some key takeaways.
Fetch, decode, dispatch, and retire are all in order stages, while issue, execute, and
complete are out of order.
The reason why this scheme is able to maintain precise state is because all changes to register
mappings happen in order, either via the dispatch stage or the retire stage.
And one last reminder of the distinction between stalling, where all younger instructions
must stall too, versus waiting, where younger instructions may bypass out of order.
To sum up, we covered two fundamental implementations of superscalar processors, scoreboard and
R10K.
An analogy of their key concepts is say multiple students are working on different projects
in the same computing cluster.
With scoreboard, these projects can be executed in any arbitrary out of order, that is, some
students who started later can still end up finishing first.
However, there's only one installation of LLVM allowed in the system at any moment.
So even though all projects are independent from each other, they may need to wait for
each other to finish, since they may need different versions of LLVM.
But with R10K, we break this hazard by installing the different versions of LLVM in temporary
directories.
We maintain precise state by using a main symbolic link that points to the most recent
version.
But projects can now run fully out of order without waiting for each other, because they
can use temporary copies of LLVM if need be.
So let's close out this lecture with a quick exercise.
The top shows an example program that has been renamed, with the contents of the map
table and free list shown over time.
The question is which physical registers are freed when each of the instructions are retired?
Take some time now to try to fill in the blanks.
So when we dispatch the add instruction, we renamed its output to P4, but when the add
retires, P4 does not go back into the free list, but rather, the original mapping of
register T1 is what goes into the free list, which is physical register P1.
So similarly, when the NOR instruction retires, the original mapping for architectural register
T3 is freed, which is P3.
Then the subtract overrides T3 again, and it ends up freeing P5, which is the physical
register that was just allocated to the NOR instruction.
And finally, the ORI instruction frees up P4, which is the physical register that was
allocated to the add instruction earlier.